Badar Al Maqbali

Muscat, Oman Badar1@live.com +96899772240

Summary

Experienced Health, Safety, and Environment Engineer with a demonstrated history of working in the Oil & Gas industry as well as the electricity sector in Oman. In addition to the research, communication, and teamwork skills, I have acquired managerial and leadership skills with completion of my MBA program where I acquired more knowledge in different disciplines such as project management, marketing, managing people...etc. Which integrated with my scientific and practical experience in the field of electrical power engineering

Experience

HSSE Engineer

Majan Electricity Company SAOC

Mar 2016 - Present (+ 5 years)

- 1. Lead the development and implementation of incident investigation, systems, processes, procedures, and controls, and continuously identify and recommend improvements while ensuring compliance with HSE guidelines, standards, and relevant legislation.
- Develop and implement corporate process and protocols of investigation of all Health, Safety, and Environmental incidents in order to identify the root cause and all the variables associated with the incidents
- 3. Develop and assure the proper standardization of incident investigation and classification across the group such as occupational and environmental diseases, classification in case of any incident involving any medical health or environmental incident in Downstream (LTI Lost Time Incident; Restricted Work Case; FAC First-aid Case; Work accidents, near misses, environmental incidents, etc.)
- 4. Deliver comprehensive corporate reports of the results of all investigations including the Root Cause Analysis and recommendations, in order to identify and implement areas of improvement and corrective actions to contribute to the continuous improvement of HSE performance
- 5. Establish and monitoring standardized processes and procedures for incident investigation and promote its dissemination across the organization
- 6. Provide corporate guidance to the parties involved in an incident investigation in order to promote the positive impact of the incident's investigation to contribute to the development and execution of the HSE long-term strategic plan in alignment with the function and organisation strategies.
- 7. Report progress against investigation findings and the corrective actions, mitigations taken, and course of corrective actions in order to avoid recurrence of the incidents
- 8. Develop and monitor the standards (quality and quantity) of training and workshops programs for leaders and employees related to incident investigation and Cause Root Analysis in order to enhance corporate capacity to identify incident causes of incidents and consolidate a safety culture
- 9. Supports regulatory compliance efforts and other programs applicable at the site including stormwater management, employee training, recordkeeping/reporting, and other associated HSE programs at the facilities.
- 10. Present regular and ad-hoc corporate management reports on new opportunities, highlight critical issues and challenges and provide strategic insight to ensure effective decision-making.
- 11. Perform analysis and interpretation of Investigation results such as common root causes, activities (e.g. lifting, manual handling, etc), repeat incident analysis, corrective and preventative actions, closing out of actions (on time, late), etc..
- 12. Lead investigator in complex investigations such as Taproot, ICAM, or Tripod BETA.

Electrical Engineer

AL Zawawi Powertech Engineering company

Aug 2015 - Mar 2016 (8 months)

- 1. manage the day to day implementation of certain approved Projects and monitor project development against milestones
- 2. Ensure that all assigned projects are delivered on time and budget in accordance with the Company's License conditions
- 3. draft technical specifications and scope of work for certain new production Projects, as required in oil and gas facilities
- 4. participate in the commissioning of all assigned Projects and Physical Effects Modelling and Quantitative Risk Assessment, experience with Shell FRED and SHEPHERD software.
- 5. follow established policies and procedures regarding the day to day operations of the designated distribution network as set out in the Distribution Area Manual
- 6. working with PDO Project Delivery (PD) as a centre of excellence for all project delivery in PDO for Amal HRSG project and tech safety management implementation.
- 7. provide a technical clarifications/justifications, compliance to standards (SPs, PRs, DEM1, DEM2), participation in assurance activities like PSUAs, VARs etc etc. and in Petroleum Development Oman (PDO) http://pdo.co.om/
- 8. comply with Shell standards and guidelines, including Sour Gas design and operations standards and guidelines

Electrical Installations Technician

Al Manara Trading

Oct 2013 - Aug 2015 (1 year 11 months)

- 1. Expertly handled single & 3 phase wiring and comply with Oman Electrical stander 4
- 2. Maintained & repaired a variety of electrical components & equipment
- 3. Inspect electrical components including circuit breakers & transformers
- 4. Implement Fire Protection standards and guidelines.
- 5. Belt effective communication to influence key stakeholders.

Education

Franklin University

Master's degree, Master Of Business Administration (2016 – 2018)

 MBA Foundations / Business Environment Managerial Economics, Marketing Management, Financial & Managerial Accounting, Human Resource Management, Operations Management, Corporate Finance, Strategic Management

University of Technology and Applied Sciences

University Degree in Engineering (Electrical Power Engineering 2009 – 2015)

Licenses & Certifications

- 1. Nebosh IGC NEBOSH
- 2. IOSH IOSH
- 3. Highfield level 5 Highfield
- 4. Green Belt Certification (GB) in lean management
- 5. ISO 9001, ISO 14001 and ISO 45001 internal auditor TUV Rheinland Arabia LLC
- 6. Bow Tie XP CGE Risk
- Oracle Database 10g Administrator Certified Master ORACLE FINANCIAL SERVICES SOFTWARE LIMITED

Achievements

- 1. Leader of MJEC HSSE Function in NAMA Integration Management System project (NIMS)
- 2. Develop Majan Electrical Safety Rules (ESR)
- 3. Train an engineers team to get the ESR authorization
- 4. Create a website to monitor and follow up ESR authorization process
- 5. Member of: incident investigation committee, electrical license committee, and documents and archives committee
- 6. Membership in Oman Society of Engineers (OSE) / (from 2013)